Okay בוקר טוב. boker tov. So today's דף daf is יד. yud-daled.
We pick up in the middle of יג עמוד ב. yud-gimmel amud-beis.
And we are dealing with of course מעשה מרכבה. ma'aseh merkavah. So
presumably everything we're talking about is not the secret stuff. And we
pick up
with... אמר ליה
רב פפא לאביי. amar lei Rav Pappa le-Abaye. אלא מעתה, ella me-ata,
דכתיב... dikhsiv... one, two, three, four, five, six, about seven, about nine
lines down in the medium-sized lines. Line starts with the word דכתיב.
dikhsiv. So we're dealing with the fact that the vision of the
faces on the Divine throne, in one verse it's a lion, an
eagle, or probably a vulture, an ox, and a human. In another
one, instead of the ox, it's a כרוב, keruv, which is a
cherub, which is explained here as like an infant's face. And it
says that because יחזקאל Yechezkel prayed to God that it should change,
because you don't want the ox that reminds God of the מעשה
עגל ma'aseh egel up there in שמים. shamayim. And again, fascinating, like
a similar statement earlier by דוד המלך David HaMelech about what types
of forces are up, what type of like the bad stuff, the
meteorological tragedies, are they kept up in heaven, are they kept down
in the earth. So on the one hand, all of the way
in which God is so transcendent and distant, and then at the
same time, people pray and change the very look of how things
look up in שמים. shamayim. Anyway, so now the גמרא Gemara says,
אמר ליה רב פפא לאביי אלא מעתה דכתיב פני האחד פני הכרוב
ופני השני פני אדם והשלישי פני אריה והרביעי פני נשר. amar lei
Rav Pappa le-Abaye ella me-ata dikhsiv pnei ha-echad pnei ha-keruv u-pnei ha-sheni
pnei adam ve-ha-shlishi pnei aryeh ve-ha-revii pnei nesher. Actually we did that
but we'll read it again. היינו פני כרוב היינו פני אדם? hainu
pnei keruv hainu pnei adam? So if you're saying a כרוב keruv
is a child, so what does it mean that one is the
face of a child and one is the face of a human?
They're both human faces. So he says, אפי רברבי ואפי זוטרי. appei
ravrivi ve-appei zutrei. No, there's the face of an adult and there's
the face of a child or little, big face and small face,
and those also become significant terms in קבלה. Kabbalah. כתיב, ksiv, כתוב
אחד אומר, kasuv echad omer,
one verse says, now we're moving from the throne to the angels,
שש כנפים שש כנפים לאחד, shesh knafayim shesh knafayim le-echad,
each angel had six wings. וכתוב אחד אומר, ve-kasuv echad omer, and
another verse, not in יחזקאל Yechezkel but in ישעיהו Yeshayahu says, וארבע
פנים לאחת וארבע כנפים לאחת להם. ve-arba panim le-achat ve-arba knafayim le-achat
lahem. Each one had four faces and had four wings. So what
is it? Six wings or four wings? גמרא Gemara says, לא קשיא.
lo kashya. כאן בזמן שבית המקדש קיים, kan bi-zman she-Beis HaMikdash kayam,
so ישעיהו Yeshayahu was at the time there was a בית המקדש,
Beis HaMikdash, כאן בזמן שאין בית המקדש קיים, kan bi-zman she-ein Beis
HaMikdash kayam, when there's no...
actually wait, that doesn't work. Oh I'm sorry, I got it reversed.
ישעיהו Yeshayahu saw six wings, I'm sorry I quoted it reversed. ישעיהו
Yeshayahu saw six wings, שש כנפים, shesh knafayim, and יחזקאל Yechezkel saw
four wings. So the גמרא Gemara says, כאן בזמן שבית המקדש קיים,
kan bi-zman she-Beis HaMikdash kayam, when there was a בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash there were six wings, and when there wasn't a בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash there were four. Now יחזקאל Yechezkel saw his vision in
exile, but it was still a few years before the destruction of
the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. The הגר"א Gra basically says that it
was like anticipating the destruction of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Okay,
so that's the difference between the six and the four. So now
the גמרא Gemara explains, כביכול, kivyakhol, it's as if, נסמטו כנפי החיות.
nismatu kanfei ha-chayot. As if the destruction of the Temple caused the
wings of the angels to become fewer.
So what happens down here again affects what's above, whether that's for
good or for bad, but again, on the one hand, this tremendous
sense of transcendence, but on the other hand, the relationship of what
happens down here to what happens above. Okay. So now רש"י Rashi
says by the way, the כביכול kivyakhol doesn't mean that it didn't
happen, it really was נסמטו כנפי החיות, nismatu kanfei ha-chayot, but כביכול
kivyakhol just meant that that's not usually an appropriate way of talking
about things relating to God, like something lacking occurred, but the reality
is that that actually, or things related to God, but that's actually
what happened. So now the גמרא Gemara says, now
of course the idea by the way, I should say, on the
one hand, you have this sense of this tremendous transcendence, the whole
גמרא Gemara before about hundreds of thousands of years to get up
to heaven, but on the other hand, the very fact that you're
having a vision and you're seeing up and you're seeing in such
concrete terms, itself basically speaks about a fundamental connection and a relationship.
So again, it is interesting about the sort of the way in
which the גמרא Gemara is dealing with how things down here impact
things up there.
Yeah, it's almost like מידת הרחמים. middat harachamim.
It's interesting to see כביכול kivyakhol
used in the context of מלאכים. malakhim. Oh I see
what you...
Oh yeah, that's a good point, like normally כביכול kivyakhol is something
you use by God and here you're even using the term כביכול
kivyakhol by angels. That's a... that's fascinating. Yeah, right, that's a very
good point. Okay, so now it says, הי מינייהו אימעטו? hai minaihu
imtu?
So which of the six... of the two... which two of the
six were reduced? Were taken... were lost after the חורבן הבית? Churban
HaBayis? So there are those that cover the face and those that
cover the legs, which two were lost? So אמר רב חננאל אמר
רב, amar Rav Chananel amar Rav, אותן שאומרות שירה בהן. otan she-omrot
shirah ba-hen. The two wings that they would use to sing to
God. כתיב הכא, ksiv hacha, it says here, ובשתים יעופף, u-vish-tayim ye'ofef,
in two they would fly, so that's not exactly singing. It says
two they cover their faces, two they cover their legs, and two
they would fly. But the flying ones are going to be identified
as the singing ones. וקרא זה אל זה. ve-kara zeh el zeh.
And they call one to another, right, and they praise God. ואמר,
ve'amar, right, קדוש קדוש קדוש. kadosh kadosh kadosh. כתיב, Ktiv, he says,
so therefore it mentions flying, but it also mentions singing to God,
praising God, קדוש קדוש קדוש. kadosh kadosh kadosh. וכתיב Uchtiv in another
verse it says, התעיף עיניך בו ואיננו. Hat'if einecha bo ve'einenu. So
that's a cute play on words. Like if you flutter your eyes,
it'll disappear.
So יעופף ye'ofef to fly, to flutter, and to flutter your eyes.
So those are the ones that disappear. And that obviously makes a
lot of sense if the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash is destroyed. There's
less שירה shira that is being said up above. And as the
גמרא's Gemara going to relate later and תוספות Tosafot relate it here
now, I'll get back to the תוספות, Tosafot, the whole connection, right,
about you know we say קדיש Kaddish below and they say קדיש
Kaddish above. וקרא זה אל זה, Vekara ze el ze, you know,
the connection of our saying שירה shira to God and we had
it before about that, about the angels are silent when we say
שירה, shira, we're silent when they say שירה, shira, one in the
night, one in the day. So if there's no בית המקדש, Beit
Hamikdash, then the שירה shira up in heaven is itself, has itself,
you know, been minimized, yes.
So wings are singing.
The wings are singing.
So it's וקרא זה אל זה. Vekara ze el ze.
Oh, I hadn't thought about that.
It's the one wing to the next wing.
Oh, that's interesting. That's interesting. That's possibly how you're reading it, how
it's reading it. Right, that's a good point.
Okay.
Okay. ורבנן אמרי, Verabbanan amri, so those, that's one approach about which
two are no longer around. ורבנן אמרי, Verabbanan amri, the rabbis say,
אותן שמכסות בהן רגליהן, otan shemechassot bahen ragleihen, the ones they used
to cover their legs. שנאמר, Shene'emar, ורגליהם רגל ישרה. veragleihem regel yeshara.
Okay, and their legs were a straight leg. So that's the vision
of יחזקאל. Yechezkel. So when he only saw four wings, but he
saw their legs, ואי לאו דאימעוט, ve'ee lav de'im'it, and if those
wings had not been the ones that were reduced, מנא הוה ידע?
mina hava yada? How did he know what the legs looked like?
He only could know what the legs looked like if they were
no longer being covered. So the גמרא Gemara says no, דילמא דגלי
וחזי ליה, dilma degali vechazi leh, that doesn't prove anything. Maybe the
wings are still there, but he saw the legs when the wings
were like a, you know, you know when you open and close
your wings. So when the legs were revealed, he saw them, but
it doesn't mean the wings weren't there. דאי לא תימא הכי, De'ee
lo teima hachi, if you don't say that, how about the other
things he saw? דמות פניהם פני אדם, Demut pneihem pnei adam, he
saw what their faces were like. הכא נמי
דאימעוט, Hacha nami de'im'it, will we say that they are lacking the
wings that covered their face? Nobody wants to say that. אלא, Ella,
and anyway you can't say they're lacking both the face wings and
the leg wings. They're only losing, lost one set. אלא דגלי וחזי
ליה, Ella degali vechazi leh, they were revealed, you know, when they
opened their wings. הכא נמי דגלי וחזי ליה, Hacha nami degali vechazi
leh, here too they were revealed. So the גמרא Gemara says wait,
הכי השתא, Hachi hashta, how's that possible? בשלמא אפי אורח ארעא לגלויי
קמיה רביה. Bishlama appei orech ar'a legalluyei kamei rabbei. It's one thing
the face,
you would reveal your face in the presence of your master. So
therefore it's possible they had those wings that cover their face and
they were, you know, they revealed their face in the presence of
God, the angels. כרעי, Karei, one's legs, לאו אורח ארעא לגלויי קמיה
רביה. lav orech ar'a legalluyei kamei rabbei. If the legs were covered
and they had wings to cover it, they would never uncover them
in the presence of God. So therefore if יחזקאל Yechezkel could see
the wings, it must be not that they basically had, could see
the legs, it must be basically that not that they had the
wings but they happened to have revealed their legs. They would never
have done such a thing. It must be fundamentally they did not
have their wings altogether. So okay, so that's the other opinion. Now
I should say, you know, again if you think about the symbolism,
one is the angels can't sing anymore to God or can't sing
with their wings. The others though is that they're like standing half
naked before God. I mean if it wasn't obvious, the גמרא Gemara
has spelled it out right now, that the problem is that nobody
would ever in the presence of, you know, God, in the presence
of the master, reveal their legs, right? That's completely disrespectful. So they're
basically standing partially naked in the presence of God. So that creates
this other sense of like, you know, being stripped of the בית
המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, right, and that sense of like, you know, being
in exile and the way in which we are now, you know,
have been, you know, have been like stripped naked or partially naked.
So it's a different type of a way in what's going down
down here reflects what's going or impacts what's going on up there.
Alright, so now the גמרא Gemara continues.
כתוב אחד אומר. Katuv echad omer.
Now let's deal with some other contradictions. One verse says, this is
in דניאל. Daniel. We're no longer
in ישעיה Yeshayahu and יחזקאל. Yechezkel. אלף אלפין ישמשוניה, Elef alfin yeshamshuneh,
thousands upon thousands or a thousand thousands, a million attend to him,
God. ורבו רבבן קדמוהי, Veribbu rivvan kadmohi, and a myriad of myriads.
So myriad is ten thousand, so ten thousand times ten thousand is
a hundred million. Anyway, are in God's presence.
יקומון, Yekumun, stand in his presence. וכתוב אחד אומר, Uchtuv echad omer,
but another verse in איוב Iyov says, היש מספר לגדודיו? Hayish mispar
legedudav? Is there any number to God's troops? So they're infinite. So
it's not just a hundred million, it's infinite. So the גמרא Gemara
says, לא קשיא, lo kashya, it's not difficult. כאן בזמן שבית המקדש
קיים כאן בזמן שאין בית המקדש קיים. kan bizman shebeit hamikdash kayam
kan bizman she'ein beit hamikdash kayam. Same thing. איוב Iyov was presumably
when there still was a בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. We don't exactly
know when איוב Iyov was. But יחזקאל Yechezkel again, oh no, דניאל
Daniel it says now. Now we're in דניאל. Daniel. דניאל Daniel clearly
was after the חורבן Churban and therefore it went down from infinite
to... hundred million. כביכול שנמעטו פמליא של מעלה *kiviyachol she-nismatu pamalya shel
ma'ala*, as if saying, again, because you know, we're not supposed to
say these types of things of God, so כביכול *kiviyachol*, what happened
was God's great family, פמליא *pamalya*, right, retinue, had become smaller. תניא
*tanya*, we taught in a ברייתא braita, *braisa*, רבי Rabbi, *Rebbi* says
משום אבא יוסי בן דוסאי *mishum Abba Yosi ben Dosai*, אלף אלפין
ישמשוניה *elef alfin yishameshuney*, מספר גדוד אחד *mispar gdud echad*. So the
thousands of thousands, the millions that attend to God, that is the
number of God's troops. One troop, you know, one what do they
call it, a legion of soldiers. ולגדודיו אין מספר *v'ligdudav ein mispar*,
and his legions are infinite. So that's how he reconciled the verse,
right? The verse in דניאל Daniel, *Daniel* that says he has a
million who attend to him, that's just the number of people in
one of his in one of his legions. But the verse in
איוב *Iyov* says he has an infinite number of legions, so it
all works out. Each legion that's infinite has a million in it.
תניא *tanya*, we taught in a ברייתא braita, *braisa*, I'm sorry, רבי
Rabbi, ירמיה בר אבא *Rabbi Yirmiyah bar Abba* אמר Amar, *amar*, אלף
אלפין ישמשוניה *elef alfin yishameshuney*, a thousand thousands attend to him, so
that's a million, זה נהר דינור Dinur *zeh Nehar Dinur*. Those are
the ones that emerge from the river of fire, שנאמר shene'emar, *shenemar*.
Now the word דינור dinur. *Dinur* means of fire, okay? It's Aramaic,
it's from the verse in דניאל Daniel *Daniel* that we're about to
read. But it also starts becoming the like proper name of this
river, נהר דינור *Nehar Dinur*. Let me actually read you the verse
in דניאל Daniel *Daniel* because we're going to be unpacking that today
or whatever, looking at that.
Fireworks in modern Hebrew are זיקוקי דינור *zikukei dinur*. Oh, really?
Yeah. We're going to get to that.
You see דניאל Daniel *Daniel* is alive and well.
Well, how about just חשמל *chashmal* and...
I know,
but I'm just saying, I'm saying that's like the word we had
yesterday. That's
like,
oh come on, everybody knows that.
Right, here we go. What? Here we go. Okay,
I'll read you the Hebrew and then I'll read you the English.
חזה הוית *chazei haveis* עד די כרסון רמיו *ad di chorsavan rmiu*
until the, ועתיק יומין יתיב Veatik yomin yetiv, *v'Atik Yomin yesiv* until
the thrones were set in place and the Ancient of Days took
his seat, God. לבושה כתלג חיור *levushei k'salag chivar*, his garment was
like a white snow, ושער ראשה כעמר נקי *usar reisheh k'amar nkei*,
and the hair of his head was like a clean wool, כרסיה
שביבין דינור Karsia shvivin dinur, *korseih shvivin dinur*,
his throne was tongues of flame, there's your דינור *dinur*, שביבין *shvivin*,
גלגלוהי נור דליק *galgalohi nur dolik*, the wheels were like a lit
flame or blazing fire, נהר דינור נגד *nehar dinur naged* so a
river דינור *Dinur* of fire stretched out, ונפק מן קדמוהי *v'nafek min
kodamohi* and came from God's presence, אלף אלפין ישמשוניה *elef alfin yishameshuney*
thousands upon thousands attended to him, ורבו רבון קדמוהי יקומון *v'ribo ribvan
kodamohi yekumun* myriads of myriads stood before him, דינא יתיב וספרין פתיחו
*dina yesiv v'sifrin p'sichu* and the he was writing, the court sat
and the books were opened. Sounds pretty relevant for Rosh Hashanah to
what's coming up in a few days. That's the vision in דניאל
*Daniel*. So let's take a look. So אלף אלפין ישמשוניה *elef alfin
yishameshuney*, those thousands of thousands that attend to him, זה נהר דינור
*zeh Nehar Dinur*, those were those that emerged from the river of
fire, שנאמר she-ne'emar, *shenemar*, נהר דינור נגד ונפק מן קדמוהי *nehar dinur
naged v'nafek min kodamohi*, this river of fire came from his presence,
אלף אלפין ישמשוניה ורבו רבון קדמוהי יקומון *elef alfin yishameshuney v'ribo ribvan
kodamohi yekumun*. Okay, so presumably though, as opposed to, seems to say
איוב *Iyov*, who said the total number of God's retinue is infinite,
but the thousands of thousands and myriad of myriads, those were just
the ones that came from this river of fire. Okay, מהיכן נפיק
*meiheichan nafik*, now where do they come out of or where does
this, you know, river of fire come from
and hence where do the angels come from? מזיעתן של חיות *mizei'asan
shel chayot*, from the sweat of the heavenly beasts, you know, the
other vision of the beasts that was seen in heaven. So their
sweat makes this river of fire and the angels emerge from that.
ולאיכן שפיך *u'l'eichan shaphich*, and where does this river pour out to?
אמר רב זוטרא בר טוביה אמר רב *amar Rav Zutra bar Tuvya
amar Rav*, על ראש רשעים בגיהנם *al rosh reshaim b'geinnom*, so this
river of fire pours out onto the head of the wicked in
גיהנם *Geinnom*, שנאמר she-ne'emar, *shenemar*, הנה סערת ה' חמה יצאה וסער מתחולל
על ראש רשעים יחול *hineh sa'aras Hashem cheimah yatza v'sa'ar mischolel al
rosh reshaim yachul*, the whirlwind of God, anger comes
out, and this again whirlwind that falls upon the head of the
wicked, יחול *yachul*, shall fall on their head. רב אחא בר יעקב
אמר *Rav Acha bar Yaakov amar*, על אשר קומטו *al asher kumtu*,
on those that have, that have that it was decreed that they
should have been created, שנאמר Sheneamar *shenemar*, as it says, אשר קומטו
בלא עת *asher kumtu b'lo eis*,
those that were, again Rashi reads this word as decreed and it
was not yet their time, נהר יוצק יסודם *nahar yutzak yesodam*, a
river that was pouring out is their foundation. Now what does this
mean, those that were decreed? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going
to explain, תניא *tanya*, we taught in a ברייתא *braisa*, אמר רבי
שמעון החסיד *amar Rabbi Shimon Hachasid*, אלו תשע מאות ושבעים וארבע דורות
*elu tesha me'os v'shivim v'arba doros*, these are the nine hundred and
seventy four generations שקומטו ליבראות *she-kumtu l'hibaros*
where it was decreed that they should have been created קודם שנברא
העולם *kodem shenivra ha'olam* before the world was created. Meaning, it's based
on the verse that says that the idea that it says דבר
צוה לאף דור *davar tziva l'elef dor*, God's command was commanded for
a thousand generations, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* reads that not that just
that the תורה Torah. *Torah*. was given for eternity and for thousands
of generations, but that the תורה Torah, *Torah* was given after a
thousand generations, or should have been given after a thousand generations. Now
if you count the generations from אדם *Adam* until מתן תורה Torah
*Matan Torah* you only get twenty-six. So what happened to the nine
hundred and seventy-four generations that should have preceded מתן תורה Torah, *Matan
Torah*? Well, God realized that the world could not wait a thousand
generations for מתן תורה Torah *Matan Torah*. So he had to speed
things up and give it after only twenty-six generations, and the other
nine hundred and seventy-four that should have been created apparently they also
would have been like real רשעים *reshaim* because that was part of
the reason why we had to speed things up because we needed
a תורה Torah, *Torah*. So therefore what's going to happen to them?
ולא נבראו *Velo nivru*, אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא ושתלן *amar HaKadosh Baruch
Hu veshatlan*, so God stood up and deposited them בכל דור ודור
*bechol dor vador*. So they get sort of distributed over time, these
nine hundred and seventy-six generations that could not have been—nine hundred and
seventy-four, excuse me, there were twenty-six. I said twenty-four, I'm—mistake. Nine hundred
and seventy-four generations, it was twenty-six until מתן תורה Torah, *Matan Torah*
that were distributed, that were distributed over all time. והינן עזי פנים
שבדור *Veheinan azai panim shebedor*, and those are the brazen people that
you find in every generation. Those were the ones that have been
distributed from the nine hundred and seventy-four that were too wicked and
were not created. Okay, so
now of course the question is why are they getting this, you
know, fire poured on their head because they're רשעים *reshaim*? That's all
very nice, but they're רשעים *reshaim* that have never had the chance
to be רשעים *reshaim* because they were never created. So תוספות Tosafos
*Tosafos* is a little bit bothered by that. So תוספות Tosafos, *Tosafos*
says, if you look at תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos*, דאיכא למאן דאמר ששתלן
בתרשישת כדאיתא שם רישון נפלו נשמתם בגיהנום ולא נבראו *d'ikah leman d'amar
sheshatlan b'tirshashit k'd'eita sham rishon naflu nishmatam b'Gehennom velo nivru*. Before it
says that they were deposited, so he
says
the first opinion was was that they were just in גיהנום *Gehennom*
and not created. ותימה הוא וכי עביד דינא בלא דינא *Veteimah hu
vechi avi dina belo dina*? Will God do judgment without justice? כי
מה פשעו להיות בגיהנום *Ki ma pashu leyos b'Gehennom*? So what are
they doing in גיהנום *Gehennom*?
Okay, you know, I mean it's one thing to say they got
spread out over all future generations, but another thing to say they
weren't created and then are in גיהנום *Gehennom* and being punished because
they would have been רשעים *reshaim*. Okay, so ונראה לפרש בשתלן שלא
נבראו ביחד *venireh lefareish b'shatlan shelo nivru beyachad*. So תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos*
says no, it all means the same thing, that they were distributed
in every generation. Okay, and therefore if they're going to be punished
with this river of fire, it's only when they actually are created
and do evil, but that's not, but they're over, you know, the
wicked people in each generation or the brazen people. That's such a
good estimation. Why? Four hundred years or so.
Oh,
good point. He had to change to ten, a thousand, he had
to change to twenty-six, right.
Good point, good point. Twenty-six by the way is also the גמטריה
*gematria* of יוד-קא-ואו-קא *Yud-Kei-Vav-Kei* for those keeping score. I don't know, anyway.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. רב עמרם בר יצחק
אמר אשר קמטו לברכה *Rav Amram bar Yitzchak amar asher kumtu livrachah*.
No, those that were decreed for blessing too. דכתיב dechtiv *Dechesiv*, הוא
דכתיב *hu dechesiv*, אלו תלמידי חכמים שמקמטין עצמן על דברי תורה Torah.
בעולם הזה *elu talmidei chachamim shemekamtin atzman al divrei Torah ba'olam hazeh*.
Not exactly sure how to translate this word מקמטין *mekamtin*. רש"י Rashi
*Rashi* before said it meant to be decreed. But anyway, somehow dedicate
themselves for תורה Torah *Torah* or have been created for תורה Torah
*Torah* in this world. הקדוש ברוך הוא מגלה להם סוד בעולם הבא
*HaKadosh Baruch Hu megaleh lahem sod ba'olam haba*. God will reveal to
them the secrets in the future, שנאמר ונהר יוצק יסודם *shene'emar v'nahar
yutzak yesodam*, the poured river is their foundation, but reading also is
their secret. So this river in איוב *Iyov* is not the river
of fire in דניאל *Daniel*. The river of fire in דניאל *Daniel*,
that's for the רשעים *reshaim*. This river, and that's where the angels
come from and that's the sweat of the heavenly חיות *chayot*. The
river in איוב *Iyov*, that's for the righteous. Okay. אמר ליה שמואל
*Amar lei Shmuel*. So now we're going to have a story. We
had some like before about trying to teach people מעשה בראשית Maaseh
Bereshit *ma'aseh bereishis*. Now we're going to have to try to teach
people מעשה מרכבה Maaseh Merkavah *ma'aseh merkavah*. Let's take a look. Oh
actually no, that's coming a little later, I jumped ahead. But first
a story. אמר ליה שמואל לחייא בר רב *Amar lei Shmuel leChiyah
bar Rav*. בר אריה *Bar Arya*,
son of the lion, meaning his father was a great person. תא
אימא לך מלתא מהני מילי מעליותא דהוה אמר אבוך *Ta eima lach
miltah mehani milei malyusa d'havi amar avuch*. Come let me tell you
one of the great things that your father used to teach. כל
יומא ויומא *Kol yoma v'yoma*, here's what your father used to teach,
every day. כל יומא ויומא נבראים מלאכי השרת מנהר דינור *Kol yoma
v'yoma nivraim malachei hashareis min nahar Dinur*. Heavenly angels are created from
the river of דינור *Dinur*. We said before that that comes from
the sweat of the חיות *chayot* and that's where the angels are
created from. ואמרי שירה shira ובטלי *Ve'amri shirah ubatli*, and then after
they say their prayer, they cease to exist. שנאמר *Shene'emar* as the
verse says, חדשים לבקרים chadashim labkarim, רבה אמונתך *chadashim labekarim rabbah emunasecha*.
New to every morning, great is your faithfulness, God. So exactly what
it means faithfulness in this context? מהרש"א *Maharsha* says it means you
show your, you know, every day you demonstrate, הקדוש ברוך הוא מחדש
בכל יום מעשה בראשית Maaseh Bereishit *HaKadosh Baruch Hu mechadesh bechol yom
ma'aseh bereishis*, not just that the world's recreated, the angels are recreated,
and they're created every day just for the one purpose of saying
שירה shira, *shirah* and then they pass and then they stop existing.
Sort of like this idea that angels, you know, exist for like
one purpose. Also sort of like, what are those bees that they
live one day and they sting you and they die or something
like that?
No? No, anyway. What?
It's not just one day, they sting you and they die. I
think there's some other insect that lives for like one day. Anyway.
All right. Anyway. So תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos* now, that's so that's the
idea. There's an interesting תוספות *Tosafos* about how this might inform the
language we say in קדושה Kedusha. *Kedushah*. If you look at תוספות
*Tosafos*... and they die or something like that? No? No anyway, one
day. What? It's not just one day, they sting you and they
die. I think there's some other insect that lives for like one
day. Anyway. All right, anyway, so תוספות, now that's, so that's the
idea, there's an interesting תוספות about how this might inform the language
we say in קדושה. Kedusha. If you look at תוספות, the previous
דף, daf, מזעת חיות. mize'at Chayos. תוספות says the following: ויוצאים ממנו
מלאכים, v'yotzim mimenu malachim, so this from this river of דינור comes
angels, ואומרים שירה ומיד נטרדים v'omrim shira u'miyad nitradim and immediately they
cease to exist. וכה מצינו במדרש, v'cho matzinu bamidrash, חדשים לבקרים, שברא
מלאכים בכל יום, shebara malachim bechol yom, ואומרים שירה וניטרדים להם, v'omrim
shira v'nitradim lahem, as it says in סמך. Somach.
Funny why he quoted a מדרש Midrash since it's the גמרא Gemara.
coming up, משום שיש אות
במלאכים. mishum sheyeish os bamalachim. That תוספות spells out why they stop
to exist because there's a sign among the angels, הקבועים, hakvuim, the
regular angels, not the ones that are newly created, but the old
hands at it, the ones that are always around, those angels, שממתינים
זה לזה לומר שירה. shemamtinim zeh lazeh lomar shira.
They know, there's a secret sign that they know when they're supposed
to start singing שירה to God. Okay, but that's because they've been
around the bend, so they know the sign. ואלו החדשים, ve'eilu hachadashim,
the new ones, שאינם יודעים הדת, she'einam yodim hadas, they don't know
about the rules, they were created and they don't know when they're
supposed to start singing שירה, ממהרים לומר שירה, memaherim lomar shira, they
begin singing as soon as they're created, ומתחייבים כליה, umitchayvim kilaya, and
since they speak out of turn and not at the right time,
they have to be destroyed. והיינו אשר תיקנו. ve'hainu asher tiknu.
I don't know what the moral message is here, but okay. בני
אנשי כנסת הגדולה, b'nei anshei knesses hagedola, וביותר, uviyoser,
and now we understand what we say in
יוצר, Yotzer, ונותנים רשות זה לזה venosnim reshus zeh lazeh to קדושה
כולם כאחד עונים ואומרים. Kedusha kulam k'echad onim v'omrim.
So they have to give permission before you say קדושה. Okay, you
gotta wait for the right time. וגם למעלה vegam lemala יוצר משרתים
yotzer mesharsim ואשר משרתיו, va'asher mesharsav,
God,
you create attendants, ואשר משרתיו כולם עומדים ברום עולם. va'asher mesharsav kulam
omdim berum olam. כולם אומרים בכל יום בורא חדשים, kulam omrim bechol
yom borei chadashim, that's יוצר משרתים, yotzer mesharsim,
you create new attendants, וניטרדים, venitradim, those just disappear right away, those
get destroyed. אבל משרתיו, aval mesharsav,
the fixed ones, הקבועים, hakvuim, those עומדים לעד. omdim la'ad. So יוצר
משרתים, yotzer mesharsim, you create new ones, but those are just the
ones you dispose of on a daily basis, ואשר משרתיו כולם עומדים
ברום עולם, va'asher mesharsav kulam omdim berum olam, but the fixed attendants,
those are staying on high and those continue to sing. So you
see the whole culture of what, you know, like disposable items,
I hope he recycles them or something.
Anyway, so there's a fascinating idea about these angels created just to
disappear and תוספות continues elaborating on that whole image and story of
what's going on there.
Do you want to say something before? Just the association with this
river of fire, so these beings are like sparks, the way sparks
come up out of a fire
and then they disappear.
Oh, that's interesting.
That's an idea. And that's why they only, oh that's a nice,
the fact that it's only moment like for a moment like a
spark that then sort of burns out instantaneously.
Seems to be consonant with the whole imagery.
Oh, that's a very nice idea. And somehow there's like some praise
to God even in that brief moment. Right, I mean, that's a
very nice point. Look, it's also a beautiful point to think about,
I mean, you know, to connect it to the previous מסכת masechet
of מועד קטן, Moed Katan, and you know, where a lot was
dealt with about children dying חס ושלום chas veshalom and those types
of issues, you know, the imagery that some people are like some
things are created just to serve God briefly, you know, that's a
helpful type of an image. So that's, you know,
okay, so now the גמרא Gemara. continues, it says the following: ופליגא
דרבי שמואל
בר נחמני, u'pliga d'Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachmani,
that argues on Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachmani, דאמר רבי שמואל בר נחמני
אמר רבי יונתן, d'amar Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachmani amar Rabbi Yonatan, כל
דיבור ודיבור שיוצא מפי הקדוש ברוך הוא נברא ממנו מלאך. kol dibur
v'dibur sheyotze mi-pi HaKadosh Baruch Hu nivra mimenu malach. Every utterance that
comes from God an angel is created, so it's not created from
the river of fire, it's created directly from God. Right, interesting question
of how much you want to directly associate them to God or
create a certain sense of distance. שנאמר, as the verse says, בדבר
השם שמים נעשו, bidvar Hashem shamayim na'asu,
with God's word the heavens were created, וברוח פיו uvi'ruach piv and
with the breath of His mouth, כל צבאם, kol tzeva'am, all of
their hosts. Okay. כתוב אחד אומר, kasuv echad omer, and one verse
says, back to the פסוקים pesukim in דניאל, לבושיה כתלג חיור, levusheih
kisalg chivar,
His cloak is like the white snow, ושער ראשה כעמר נקא, u'se'ar
reisheh k'amar neka,
and the hair of His head is like white wool, if like
clean wool, וכתיב uch'siv and another verse says, קווצותיו תלתלים שחורות כעורב,
kvutzosav taltalim shechoros ka'orev, that God's locks are like, you know, the
layered locks are black as a raven. So are they white or
are they black? So the גמרא Gemara says לא קשיא, lo kashya,
כאן בישיבה כאן במלחמה. kan bi-yeshiva kan be-milchama. One is when God
is sitting, meaning like in council acting as a sage, and one
is when God is going out to war. דאמר מר, d'amar mar,
אין לך נאה בישיבה אלא זקן, ein lecha na'eh bi-yeshiva ela zaken,
so what's appropriate for one who is sitting like in council
is being an elder, or you know, older, ואין לך נאה במלחמה
אלא בחור ve'ein lecha na'eh be-milchama ela bachur is youth.
Okay, so God looks like a youth right when He's in war
and He looks like an elder when He's in the ישיבה. yeshiva.
It's like they say in the אנעים זמירות, An'im Zemiros, right? What's
the line? What's the line in אנעים זמירות? An'im Zemiros?
קווצותיו תלתלים שחורות כעורב.
kvutzosav
taltalim shechoros ka'orev.
Yeah, no, but
it's like something like about how you've been imagined in different ways,
right? What is it? דימו אותך ולא כפי ישך. dimu oscha v'lo
kefi yeshcha.
זקנה ובחרות. Zikna uvacharut. What is it?
זקנה ביום דין ובחרות ביום קרב. Zikna beyom din uvacharut beyom kerav.
Yes, exactly that, exactly that. Right? It's this גמרא. Gemara? It's this
גמרא. Gemara דמו אותך ברוב חזיונות, Dimu otcha berov chezionot,
they have prepared you with many visions, הנך אחד בכל דמיונות, Hinecha
echad bechol dimyonot, but ultimately you're one in all the images. יחזו
בך זקנה ובחרות, Yechezu becha zikna uvacharut, they saw you both in
old age and in youth, ושער ראשך בשיבה ושחרות, Usear roshcha beseyva
veshacharut, the hair of your
head with hoary head and black hair. זקנה ביום דין ובחרות ביום
קרב. Zikna beyom din uvacharut beyom kerav.
So the being an elder is in the day of judgment, ישיבה,
yeshivah, again that whole sense of judgment, and youth in the time
of war, כאיש מלחמה ידיו רב לו. Keish milchama yadav rav lo.
So there you go, that's exactly based on this גמרא Gemara and
that פסוקים. psukim. By the way, we should mention the יום דין
yom din here on the ישיבה yeshivah as I read from you
the פסוק pasuk in דניאל and I'm sure it's directly probably the
imagery that informs some of the imagery of ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah
is God sitting with the books open in front of him. That
was exactly the image in דניאל of the vision of God. Yes,
Charlie.
Did רמב"ם Rambam comment on this section of גמרא?
Gemara רמב"ם's Rambam's done I don't know he did not do a
line by line commentary as I said when we started this פרק,
perek, רמב"ם Rambam reads certainly the general category of מעשה בראשית as
physics and you know astronomy, so the science of the natural world,
and מעשה מרכבה Maaseh Merkavah, theology but understanding it very much in
the rationalist sense. So what he would say of all this I
imagine he would say that it's all a משל. mashal. Okay.
All right, moving on. Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. כתוב אחד אומר, Katuv
echad omer,
one verse says, כרסיה שביבין דינור,
his throne is like flames of fire. Again, דינור. וכתוב אחד אומר,
Vekatuv echad omer, and
another verse says right there in the same section, עד די כרסוון
רמיו, Ad di chorsavan remiyu, until the thrones are set up, ועתיק
יומין יתיב, and the Ancient of Days sits upon them. So is
it throne or thrones? So the גמרא Gemara says לא קשיא, lo
kashya, כאן אחד לו וכאן אחד לדוד, kan echad lo vekan echad
le-David, one throne for him and one throne for the other king,
for the earthly king, for דוד. David. כדתניא, Kedetanya, like we taught
in a ברייתא, אחד לו ואחד לדוד, echad lo ve-echad le-David, דברי
רבי עקיבא. divrei Rabbi Akiva. That's what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says.
אמר לו רבי יוסי הגלילי, Amar lo Rabbi Yose HaGelili, so רבי
יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGelili says to him, עקיבא, עד מתי אתה
עושה שכינה חול? Akiva, ad matai ata oseh Shechina chol? Akiva, how
long are you going to make the Divine Presence into something secular?
You're putting a human being up there on the throne next to
God? Completely inappropriate. אלא אחד לדין ואחד
לצדקה. Ela echad ledin ve-echad letzdedaka. Therefore the two different attributes of
God, right? And again remember it's a vision of God sitting in
judgment. It's ממש, mamash, you know, the ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah imagery,
right? So one is the throne of דין, din, justice, and the
other is the throne of לצדקה, letzdedaka, of like, צדקה tzedaka often
is righteousness but here it means more of like compassion, of doing
kindness. So therefore it's not two things, it's not God and דוד,
David, it's only God up there, but God has two thrones, right?
And we have that imagery like God removes himself from the throne
of דין din and goes to the throne of רחמים. rachamim. So
that's the imagery here. Which mode is God judging the world in?
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says, קיבלה מיניה או לא קיבלה
מיניה? Kibla minei o lo kibla minei? Did רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
accept this critique or not? תא שמע, Ta shema, come and hear,
we have a ברייתא, אחד לדין ואחד לצדקה, echad ledin ve-echad letzdedaka,
דברי רבי עקיבא. divrei Rabbi Akiva. Oh, so רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
wound up saying what רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGelili said to
him. So obviously he accepted the critique and now he repeated this
saying, that two thrones, a throne of justice and a throne of
kindness or compassion. אמר לו רבי אלעזר בן עזריה, Amar lo Rabbi
Elazar ben Azarya, so רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azarya
said to him, he wasn't happy. עקיבא, מה לך אצל הגדה? Akiva,
ma lecha etzel aggada? Akiva, what what are you doing here by
הגדה? aggada? Like, okay, you say one thing, somebody corrects you, so
you say what the other person said, like, you know, this isn't
your conversation.
כלך מדבריך, Kelach midevarecha, leave your words, stop talking, and go אצל
נגעים ואהלות. etzel negaim ve-oholot. Go to the really hard parts of
ש"ס, Shas, נגעים ואהלות, Negaim ve-Oholot, the complicated halakhic parts. You're the
master there, nobody else can, you know, hold a match to you
there. Go there, let us talk about הגדה. aggada. Okay.
אלא, כאן לכיסא וכאן לשרפרף. Ela, kan lekisei vekan lesharfraf. So this,
so רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azarya did not even
like the idea of God having two thrones. That still suggests some
sense of multiplicity in the presence, you know, related to God, even
if it's not another being, but some sense of a non-total singularity.
So it's not two thrones. It is a throne and a footstool.
Okay. כיסא לשבת עליו, Kisei lashevet alav, the throne to sit on,
שרפרף להדום רגליו, sharfraf le-hadom raglav, and the footstool for his feet,
שנאמר השמים כסאי והארץ הדום רגלי. shene'emar Hashamayim kisei veha'aretz hadom raglay.
Okay. So there you go, that makes it better. So one also
wonders in all of these things if there is also some concern,
you know, either about, you know, about other gnosticism or Christianity and
other types of things that have to deal with, you know, questions
about the total singularity of God, particularly the issue of דוד David
who's a king, you know, and from דוד David comes the משיח,
Mashiach, the משיח, Mashiach, right, which we understand obviously in very earthly
terms, but it's still
on a, you know.
It could be perhaps a slight
indication of the primacy of אגדתא Agaddata of אגדתא. Agaddata. You know,
in other words, listen, you're like a halachist. Right? Go back and
do your like technical stuff.
Right. I don't know.
You're not a... you don't get this. Leave that to us. Like
the big picture.
Right. Okay, but you're inserting all of that, all of that subtext
you just inserted.
Okay. There, I'm
just saying you could say the exact opposite. You do the real
stuff. This is the נרשקייט. narishkeit. You don't... but that's not your
field, let us do it. Okay. Just...
I understand. I'm just saying, I'm just saying, but the thing is,
this isn't your field. Whether what type of a hierarchy is created
between the two fields is not in the text. But they're basically
saying, you know what, leave the אגדתא Agaddata to us. This is
not your, this is not your thing. Okay, yes.
Yeah, רש"י has in his commentary in דניאל has a very different
take on this context.
Okay fine, I am sure he does.
But I did not check where he might have gotten it.
Oh I don't know, I don't know. It is also worth noting
by the way that with all that they're telling Rabbi Akiva you
have nothing to do with these discussions, it's well accepted, you know,
by there... I mean there's strong indications, you know, as we're going
to see by רבי עקיבא נכנס לפרדס, Rabbi Akiva nichnas l'Pardes, other
indications as well that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva was a mystic. So
it is interesting, you know. Now, is mysticism the exact same and
trying to read some type of a, you know, of a state,
of an alternative state of being? Is that the same as being
able to interpret these types of verses and being a master of
אגדתא? Agaddata?
Not
necessarily.
Not every Kabbalist can give a good sermon. Exactly. But it is
interesting. It's not like he was just a rationalist, you know, halachist,
רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. Okay. Anyway, so now the גמרא Gemara continues.
ואמר רב אמי שמונה עשרה קללות קילל ישעיה את ישראל. V'amar Rav
Ami shmoneh esreh klalot kilel Yeshayah et Yisrael. So now we're shifting
gears a little bit.
18 curses ישעיהו Yeshayahu cursed Israel like you know, told them about
all the terrible things that were going to happen to them when
the temple was going to be destroyed. ולא נתקררה דעתו עד שאמר
להם המקרא הזה, V'lo nitkarera da'ato ad she'amar lahem hamikra hazeh, and
he didn't sort of calm down until he got to this verse,
which is at the end of the list of predictions you know
and curses in ישעיהו. Yeshayahu. יהבו הנער בזקן והנקלה בנכבד. Yihavu hana'ar
bazaken v'hanikleh banichbad.
The youth will lord over, bully,
over the old and the נקלה nikleh which is the opposite of
נכבד, nichbad, right? נכבד nichbad is from the word כבד, kaved, heavy.
So the weighty you know and the honored will, you know, as
will be sort of lorded over and bullied by the נקלה, nikleh,
by the lowly. Okay. And that was sort of like the worst
thing to say, which is interesting. He doesn't elaborate on why that's
worse than everything that preceded, but now we're going to spell it
all out. עשרה קללות מאי ניהו. Asarah klalot mai ninhu. What were
the ten curses? דכתיב the verse says: כי הנה האדון ה' צבאות
מסיר מירושלים ומהודה משען ומשענה. Ki hineh ha'Adon Hashem Tzevaot mesir mi'Yerushalayim
u'meYehuda mishen u'mishenah. The Lord of hosts will remove from Jerusalem and
from Judea
a support and a support, a support and a and, right, and
I don't know what's a synonym for support.
Okay. Anyway, כל משען לחם וכל משען מים, kol mishen lechem v'chol
mishen mayim, all support of bread and all support of water. גיבור
ואיש מלחמה, gibor v'ish milchamah, a mighty person and a man of
war. שופט ונביא, shofet v'navi, a judge and a prophet. וקוסם, v'kosem,
which is interesting, קוסם kosem is normally somebody that's a necromancer or
magic, so we'll see what the גמרא gemara does with that. וזקן
v'zaken and an elder. שר חמישים, sar chamishim, an officer of 50.
ונשוא פנים, u'nesu fanim, someone of lifted up face, an honorable person.
ויועץ, v'yoetz, an
advisor. וחכם חרשים, v'chacham charashim, wise in literally חרשים charashim which means
like in craft, skilled craftsmen. ונבון לחש, u'navon lachash, understanding of לחש,
lachash, which also might mean some type of like a you know
of incantations, but obviously the גמרא gemara is not going to explain
it that way. ונתתי נערים שריהם, V'natati nearim sareihem, so all of
these leaders are going to be removed and wise people. ונתתי נערים
שריהם V'natati nearim sareihem instead I will give the youth as their
masters. ותעלולים ימשלו בם V'taalulim yimshalu bam and and you know and
babes will rule over them. And the end of the verse that
the גמרא Gemara sticks in because if you've been counting that's not
ten yet. So the end of the verse is: וניגש
העם איש באיש ואיש ברעהו V'niggash ha'am ish b'ish v'ish b'reehu and
one person, people will fight one against the other. And then it
says that final verse about the נער na'ar will bully the זקן
zaken and the נקלה בנכבד. nikleh banichbad. Okay so those are the
ten curses until you got to the final one that we saw
before. What? 18?
Oh שמונה עשרה. shmoneh esreh. I'm sorry. 18. I don't know why
I said עשרה asarah because I skipped the word שמונה. shmoneh. 18.
Anyway, count it. Somehow there's 18 there. Okay, I have to admit
I did not count. Okay, so משען mishen maybe we can do
the counting now. All right. משען, mishen, number one, אלו בעלי מקרא,
elu baalei mikra, those that know פסוקים. psukim. What? 18? 18? Oh,
שמונה עשרה. shmoneh esrei. I'm sorry. 18. I don't know why I
said עשרה esrei because I skipped the word שמונה. shmoneh. 18. Anyway,
count it. Somehow there's 18 there. Okay, I have to admit I
did not count. Okay, so משען, mishan, maybe we can do the
counting now. Alright, משען, mishan, number one. אלו בעלי מקרא. eilu ba'alei
mikra. Those that know פסוקים. psukim. Okay, so the גמרא's Gemara going
to interpret almost all of this from it's from the lens of
תורה. Torah. By ומשענה, u-mash'ana, the other, in the feminine, the support,
אלו בעלי משנה, eilu ba'alei mishnah, which by the way almost sounds
like the word ומשענה u-mash'ana and is in the feminine, משנה. mishnah.
Okay, so that's people who know תורה, Torah, people know משנה, mishnah,
that's two. כגון רבי יהודה בן תימא וחבריו. k'gon rabbi yehuda ben
teima v'chaveirav. Like רבי יהודה בן תימא Rabbi Yehuda ben Teima and
his and his friends they like were complete masters of the משנה.
mishnah. איכא ביני רב פפא ורבנן. ika beinei rav pappa v'rabbanan. Now
there's a debate of רב פפא Rav Pappa and רבנן. rabbanan. חד
אמר שש מאות סדרי משנה. chad amar sheish mei'ot sidrei mishnah. One
says in the time of ישעיהו Yeshayahu there were six hundred סדרי
sidrei of משנה. mishnah. So that was what was lost. We had
we had the real mastery of משנה mishnah and all of the
teachings, there was much more תורה Torah that has been lost to
us. Six hundred orders of
משנה. mishnah. וחד אמר שבע מאות סדרי משנה. v'chad amar sheva mei'ot
sidrei mishnah. Seven hundred orders of משנה. mishnah. Actually, not ten times,
a hundred times because now talking about about מסכתות, masechtot, talking about
סדרים. sedarim. So instead of six סדרים, sedarim, they were six hundred
and one says seven hundred. Okay, so that was lost. So מקרא,
mikra, משנה. mishnah. כל משען לחם, kol mishan lechem, אלו בעלי תלמוד.
eilu ba'alei talmud. So those who are masters of the תלמוד Talmud
of you know the analysis, שנאמר, לכו לחמו בלחמי ושתו ביין מסכתי,
lechu lachamu b'lachmi u-sh'tu b'yayin masachti, come and eat in my bread
and drink the wine of my anointing. So so that again how
exactly that proves that bread is תלמוד Talmud is not clear, but
obviously that is the more like the basic thing that fills you
up, that's the thing that you know is the staple of life
from the גמרא's Gemara perspective is the תלמוד. Talmud.
You notice the parallel in the פסוק pasuk between the word לחמי
lachmi and the word מסכתי? masachti?
Oh, that's cute. מסכת. masechet. Oh, I didn't think about that. I
was thinking there might be a play on the word like מלחמה
milchama because like מלחמתה של תורה. milchamta shel Torah. But that's cute.
מסכתי. masachti. I hadn't thought about that. Very nice. Okay, so that's
three. וכל משען מים, v'chol mishan mayim, water, אלו בעלי אגדה, eilu
ba'alei aggadah, שמושכין לבו של אדם כמים, she-moshchin libo shel adam k'mayim,
באגדה. be-aggadah. That draws your heart like you know like water flows,
you know it's flowing, it's drawing your heart. Doesn't say that it's
a necessity of life like water. Okay, getting back to another question
about their relative relationship. So now we have תלמוד Talmud and אגדה,
aggadah, that's four. גיבור זה בעל שמועות. gibbor zeh ba'al shmu'ot. גיבור
gibbor is a person who knows many like teachings. Again exactly how
that's different than משנה, mishnah, presumably that's teachings more of like of
אמוראים amora'im teachings. Of course this is all anachronistic this time of
ישעיהו. Yeshayahu. But anyway somebody who's a master of many traditions. Okay,
what are we up to? Five. ואיש קוסם, v'ish kosem, I'm sorry,
I skipped the line, ואיש מלחמה, v'ish milchama, person of war, זה
שיודע לישא וליתן במלחמתה של תורה. zeh she-yodei'a lisha v'leitan b'milchamta shel
Torah. There's the מלחמה milchama analysis. Somebody who knows how to like
fight the war of תורה, Torah, really good at the sort of
you know analysis and argumentation. What do we have? Six? Seven. שופט
זה דיין. shofet zeh dayan. So שופט shofet is a judge, שדן
דין אמת לאמיתו, she-dan din emet l'amito, who does his true justice.
נביא כמשמעו. navi k'mashma'o. נביא navi is clear what that means. I
think we're up to eight. קוסם זה מלך. kosem zeh melech. קוסם
kosem which is a difficult one right because it's like a necromancer.
No, that's a king, שנאמר, קסם על שפתי מלך. kesem al siftei
melech. Like you know a charm
is on the lips of the king. Okay so that's nine. זקן
זה שראוי לישיבה. zaken zeh she-ra'uy lishiva. זקן zaken is somebody who
is worthy of sitting in like the council of sages. So we're
up to ten. שר חמישים, sar chamishim, אל תקרי שר חמישים al
tikrei sar chamishim אלא שר חומשים, ella sar chumashim, שיודע לישא וליתן
בחמישה חומשי תורה. she-yodei'a lisha v'leitan b'chamisha chumshei Torah. Somebody who's a
master I guess it's better than מקרא. mikra. בעלי מקרא ba'alei mikra
is maybe just to have it memorized. Here people that really know
how to analyze it and discuss it. דבר אחר, davar acher, שר
חמישים, sar chamishim, כדרבי אבהו, k'de-rabbi abbahu, דאמר רבי אבהו, d'amar rabbi
abbahu, מכאן שאין מעמידין מתורגמן על הציבור פחות מחמישים שנה. mikan she-ein
ma'amidin meturgeman al ha-tzibbur pachot mi-chamishim shana. Somebody does not get to
be the מתורגמן, meturgeman, the translator for the community, less than fifty
years old because obviously that's a position of a lot of responsibility,
making the תורה Torah intelligible to the people. So that is the
שר sar in the sense of even being a master. It's not
just the lowly job to be able to translate, also still the
connection to חומשים chumashim though. Okay. To to the מקרא. mikra. ונשוא
פנים, u-nesu fanim, זה שנושאים פנים לדורו בעבורו. zeh she-nos'im panim l'doro
ba'avuro. So somebody who you know that is the respect is shown
to the entire generation for this person's sake. למעלה, l'ma'ala, in terms
of respect of heaven shown to the people, so כגון רבי חנינא
בן דוסא. k'gon rabbi chanina ben dosa. Like רבי חנינא בן דוסא
Rabbi Chanina ben Dosa referring to other גמרות gemarot where רבי חנינא
בן דוסא Rabbi Chanina ben Dosa says like the whole world is
sustained because of the merit of רבי חנינא בן דוסא. Rabbi Chanina
ben Dosa. So the whole you know in heaven they show merit
to they show favor to the whole generation because of him. למטה,
l'mata, favor shown below, כגון רבי אבהו בי קיסר. k'gon rabbi abbahu
bei keisar. Like רבי אבהו Rabbi Abbahu who was respected in the
קיסר's keisar house. So that's different people that who command respect. ויועץ,
v'yo'etz, שיודע לעבר שנים ולקבוע חודשים. she-yodei'a l'abeir shanim u-likbo'a chodashim. Sort
of you know יועץ yo'etz which is counsel but something that requires
like a lot of very specialized you know knowledge, it's somebody that
knows how to do the
intercalation of the years and of and to establish the months. וחכם,
v'chacham, זה תלמיד המחכים את רבותיו. zeh talmid ha-machkim et rabbotav. And
a חכם chacham is a student who can sharpen his rabbis by
his insights and questions. חרשים. charashim. So we're separating the word חכם
chacham from חרשים. charashim. בשעה שפותח בדברי תורה הכל נעשים כחרשים. be-sha'ah
she-potei'ach b'divrei Torah ha-kol na'asim k'charashim. Every when he opens his mouth
in the words of תורה, Torah, everybody else comes to be like
a you know חרש, cheresh, like somebody who cannot hear or cannot
speak, he silences everybody else. ונבון זה המבין דבר מתוך דבר. Venavon
zeh hamevin davar mitoch davar. חרס Cheres which might mean like pottery
also maybe. ונבון זה המבין דבר מתוך דבר, Venavon zeh hamevin davar
mitoch davar, as one who's understanding is somebody can infer one thing
from another. לחש, Lachash, whispering or incantations, זה שראוי למסור לו דברי
תורה שניתנו בלחש. zeh sheraui limsor lo divrei Torah shenitnu belachash. This
is the type of person you can give the secret תורה, and
I will remind you that the גמרא Gemara before said the only
person you can tell over, I forget if it was מעשה בראשית
or מעשה מרכבה, Ma'aseh Merkavah. but it was somebody who was and
it quoted this פסוק, pasuk, right? It was שר חמישים ונשוא פנים
ויועץ וחכם חרשים ונבון לחש, Sar chamishim venesu panim veyoetz vechacham charashim
venavon lachash, etc. That was the גמרא Gemara earlier, right? It says,
yeah, אין מוסרין דברי תורה אמר רבי אמי אין מוסרין סתרי תורה
אלא למי שיש בו חמישה דברים שר חמישים ונשוא פנים ויועץ וחכם
חרשים ונבון לחש. Ein mosrin divrei Torah amar Rabbi Ami ein mosrin
sitrei Torah ela lemi sheyesh bo chamishah devarim sar chamishim venesu panim
veyoetz vechacham charashim venavon lachash. So the word לחש lachash here is
at the end. Who do you give the לחש lachash to? The
person who has all of these
qualities. Okay, ונתתי נערים שריהם. Venatati nearim sareihem. Now the final verse,
I will give the youth as their or I'm getting to the
end, I will give the youth as their
masters. מאי ונתתי נערים שריהם? Mai venatati nearim sareihem? אמר רבי אלעזר
אלו בני אדם שמנוערים מן המצוות. Amar Rabbi Elazar elu benei adam
shemnoarim min hamitzvot. It can't just be young because we're translating all
of this about מצוות mitzvot and תורה. So these are the people
that are like are completely emptied of מצוות, mitzvot, okay? As opposed
to all of the people that were the real תורה scholars and
the leaders and so on. So and now the people empty of
מצוות mitzvot will be the leaders. ותעלולים ימשלו בם, Vetaalulim yimshalu bam,
and babes will rule over them. So there's going to be a
read that says the Aramaic word תעלה taala which means a fox.
אמר רב פפא בר יעקב תעלה בני תעלה. Amar Rav Pappa bar
Yaakov taala benei taala. So תעלולים taalulim in the double foxes, son
of foxes, so like you know, sort of like
lowly people who descend from lowly people. ולא נתקררה דעתו Velo nitkarerah
daato and even after all this ישעיהו Yeshayahu wasn't put to rest
עד שאמר להם ירהבו הנער בזקן והנקלה בנכבד. ad sheamar lahem yirahavu
hanaar bazaken vehanikleh banichbad. אלו בני אדם שמנוערים מן המצוות, Elu benei
adam shemnoarim min hamitzvot, people that are emptied of מצוות. mitzvot.
ירהבו, Yirahavu, they will lord over or
bully, ירהבו במי שממולא במצוות כרימון. yirahavu bemi shememula bemitzvot kerimon. Somebody
who is filled with מצוות mitzvot like a pomegranate, which is a
phrase the גמרא uses elsewhere. Not exactly clear to me how it's
getting that out of the word זקן, zaken, but okay. But anyway,
clearly to create the
contrast. והנקלה בנכבד Vehanikleh banichbad and the lowly, the despised with with
the honored will rule over the honored. יבוא מי שחומרות דומות לו
כקלות. Yavo mi shechumrot domot lo kekalot. So it's going to really
read קולא kula and חומרא, chumra, right? הנקלה. Hanikleh. So יבוא מי
שחומרות דומות לו כקלות, yavo mi shechumrot domot lo kekalot, somebody who
will come somebody who the most weighty things in the תורה and
in הלכה halacha they treat as very light and as
trivial. וירהבו במי שקלות דומות עליו כחמורות. Veyirahavu bemi shekalot domot alav
kechamurot. People who are so you know pious that even the most
lightest things they treat as the most heavy. All right, so that
again what that's all doing here is not clear except for the
second middle section where it's about here are the people that you
can tell over לחש, lachash, you can tell over סתרי תורה sitrei
Torah are the people that have these attributes which is going to
back to a גמרא we had earlier. Yeah, can the שמונה עשרה
Shemoneh Esrei be seen as a תיקון tikun in some way for...
what? The שמונה עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei, the eighteen
and then the nineteen?
Oh, interesting. The eighteen, eighteen things and then the nineteen ברכות, berachot,
a תיקון tikun for this. That's a nice ווארט. vort. I don't
know, that's a nice ווארט. vort. Okay. אמר רב קטינא. Amar Rav
Ketina. Says רב קטינא. Rav Ketina. ואפילו בשעת כשלונה של ירושלים לא
פסקו מהם בעלי אמנה. Veafilu beshaat kishlonah shel Yerushalayim lo paseku mehem
baalei amanah. Now that this פסוק pasuk is talking about how all
of these leaders and the wise men and the religious will be
wiped out of you know of ירושלים Yerushalayim at the time of
the חורבן. churban. Even when this happened and no matter how low
they fell, fell, people who were trustworthy never stopped. There were always
somebody in there that you could trust. שנאמר as the verse says,
כי יתפוש איש באחיו בית אביו שמלה לכה קצין תהיה לנו. Ki
yitposh ish beachiv beit aviv simlah lachah katzin tihyeh lanu. One person
will grab to his brother they'll
say, you have a
cloak, you should be a ruler over us. So in the simple
sense it's basically talking about how lowly the people will have fallen
that somebody who has even a little thing just like he has
a cloak to his name, he's worthy of being the leader. But
they're going to read it again through the lens of תורה. And
so say lost all the leaders who clearly were the people who
were masters of תורה, now they're going to be looking for somebody
who has a little תורה who can be their leader. Okay so
let's take a look. דברים שבני אדם מתכסים כשמלה ישנם תחת ידך.
Devarim shebenei adam mitkasim kesimlah yeshnam tachat yadecha. Things that people hide
like a cloak, you don't want to lend out a cloak, you
know, you don't want to lend your clothes out. So
you have those, you have תורה, and you should be our leader.
Okay, people don't want to talk about תורה because then they'll be
shown to not have it. But we know that you actually have
it. והמכשלה הזאת, Vehamachshelah hazot, but this stumbling. מאי והמכשלה הזאת? Mai
vehamachshelah hazot? דברים שאין בני אדם עומדים עליהם אלא אם כן נכשל
בהם. Devarim sheein benei adam omdim aleihem ela im ken nichshal bahem.
Things that people don't stand
on meaning
that they don't own until they have actually tripped over them, which
is basically what the גמרא said about a person is not עומד
על דברי תורה, omed al divrei Torah, on words of תורה, until
you make a mistake and then you really you know put your
attention to it and you internalize it. internalize it because you've actually
made a mistake about it and you have to learn from your
mistake. So these types of things, these areas of תורה *Torah*, ישם
תחת ידך *yesham takhat yadekha*, you have this. You should be our
leader. וישא ביום ההוא לאמר *Veyisa bayom hahu leimor*. Now, but he'll
rise up that day saying, לא אהיה חובש ובביתי אין לחם ואין
שמלה *lo ehye khovesh uveveiti ein lekhem ve-ein simla*. I will not
be a, you know, leader. I, my, I do not have bread,
I do not have a cloth. Again, this is in the literal
sense of the verse, now as the גמרא *Gemara* is going to
explain it. לא תשימוני קצין עם *lo teshimuni ktzin am*. Do not
make me a leader of the people. And now we're, now we're
going to sort of reinterpret that verse. וישא *Veyisa*, will lift up.
אין נישא אלא לשון שבועה *ein nisa ela leshon shvua*. That means
he'll take an oath. שנאמר *She-ne'emar*, as the verse says, לא תשא
את שם ה' אלוהיך לשוא *lo tisa et shem Hashem Elokeikha lashav*.
Okay, don't lift up God's name. So he will take the, so
he will take an oath. That's וישא ביום ההוא *Veyisa bayom hahu*.
Now, what is he saying? לא אהיה חובש *Lo ehye khovesh*. So
as opposed to where this is future, the גמרא *Gemara* is going
to read it in the past. לא הייתי מחובשי בית המדרש *Lo
hayiti mikhovshei Beit ha-Midrash*. I was not from those people that would
be conquerors in the house of the, in the study halls. You
know, I'm not, I'm not a תלמיד חכם *talmid khakham*. Don't come
to me. I don't know any תורה *Torah*. Okay. ובביתי אין לחם
ואין שמלה *Uveveiti ein lekhem ve-ein simla*. I don't have bread and
I don't have a garment. שאין בידי לא מקרא ולא משנה *She-ein
beyadi lo mikra velo mishna*. I don't have, you know, I don't
know פסוקים *psukim*. I don't know משנה *mishna*. ולא גמרא *velo Gemara*.
And I don't know גמרא *Gemara*. Again, going back to the לחם
*lekhem* is probably the גמרא *Gemara*. I don't know which is the
מקרא *mikra* here, but going back to similar types of metaphors that
the גמרא *Gemara* was interpreting earlier verses. Okay. So anyway, so look,
here's a guy, they want him to be leader because he thinks
he's one of these few, again, through the גמרא *Gemara*'s lens, he's
one of the few people they think might still know a little
תורה *Torah*. And he refuses. So you see, even when they fall
so low that nobody knows תורה *Torah* anymore and those people are
all gone, people will at least still be honest. He'll at least
refuse to take that position. So the גמרא *Gemara* says who says
it's honesty that's doing it? The גמרא *Gemara* says ודילמא שאני התם
דאמרי ליה גמירנא *Vedilma shani hatam de-amri leih gmirna*. Maybe it's different
there because if he says to them, I know תורה *Torah*, thank
you very much, I will be the leader, I do know תורה
*Torah*. אמרו amru, ליה אימא לן *Amru leih eima lan*. So tell
us over דברי תורה *divrei Torah*. Tell us over some teaching. So
therefore, of course he's honest. It's because he'll be shown up. Right?
He can't take, he can't say he has it because then it
will turn out that he's clearly lying. But it's not fundamentally about
being honest. So the גמרא *Gemara* says no. הוה ליה למימר גמר
ושכח *Hava leih lemeimar gamar veshakhakh*. No, because he could have said
you know what, you're right, I had תורה *Torah*, but I forgot
it all. So and as opposed to saying
I never learned. So that already is a level of
honesty to say I never learned rather than just saying I had
and I lost. I just have to tell you this great line
that one of my students said to me right the year before
he got סמיכה *smikha*. I saw him in the בית מדרש *Beit
Midrash* and he was being מעביר סדרה *ma'avir sedra* there with like
רש"י *Rashi* or something. And
I said to
him, I said, oh, you know, it's really good being מעביר סדרה
*ma'avir sedra*. He says Rabbi Lindsay, he says you know why I'm
being מעביר *ma'avir* the פרשה *parsha* with רש"י *Rashi*? I said no,
why? He said because until now, if somebody were to ask me
what does רש"י *Rashi* say
on this פסוק *pasuk*, I'd have to say I don't know. But
now I can say I don't remember. There you go. That's exactly
this גמרא *Gemara*. Okay, anyway.
So the גמרא *Gemara* says מאי לא אהיה חובש *Mai lo ehye
khovesh*? What
does it mean
that I was not a, like a חובש *khovesh*, a conqueror, we'll
see how it explains חובש *khovesh*. לא אהיה חובש כלל *Lo ehye
khovesh klal*. So, I'm sorry, no, that's ending at that point. מאי
לא אהיה חובש לא אהיה חובש כלל *Mai lo ehye khovesh lo
ehye khovesh klal*. He says I was not a חובש *khovesh*. It
means I never, I never learned תורה *Torah*. Not just that
I knew it and I forgot. So that's the honesty. איני *Eeini*?
Is this really true? והאמר רבא *Ve-ha-amar Rava*, didn't רבא *Rava* say
לא חרבה ירושלים עד שפסקו ממנה בעלי אמנה *Lo kharva Yerushalayim ad
she-pasku mimena ba'alei amana*? That ירושלים *Yerushalayim* was not destroyed until any
people of trustworthiness were completely ceased from it, destroyed from it. שנאמר
*She-ne'emar*, as the verse says, שוטטו בחוצות ירושלים *Shotetu be-khutzot Yerushalayim*. Go
seek out in the, you know, and in the streets of ירושלים
*Yerushalayim*. וראו נא ודעו ובקשו ברחובותיה *U-re'u na u-de'u u-vakshu bi-rekhovoteiha*. See
and know and seek out in its streets. אם תמצאו איש אם
יש עושה משפט מבקש אמונה ואסלח לה *Im timtze'u ish im yesh
ose mishpat mevakesh emuna ve-eslakh la*. If you'll find a person, if
there is one doing justice, who is seeking after, you know, after
honesty and trustworthiness, I'll forgive it. So you see there was nobody
left. The גמרא *Gemara* says לא קשיא *Lo kashya*. It's not difficult.
הא בדברי תורה הא במשא ומתן *Ha be-divrei Torah ha be-masa u-matan*.
That's such a good answer. So one is when it comes to
תורה *Torah*. If people choose to be honest and admit you never
learned there, there will always be people that will be honest about
their תורה *Torah* knowledge. When it comes to money, when it comes
to business, nobody honest is left. Okay. בדברי תורה הוו *Be-divrei Torah
havu*. When it comes to תורה *Torah*, being honest about your תורה
*Torah* knowledge, people will be okay to be honest, actually talk about
how far they've fallen, that they're not embarrassed to admit that they
don't know תורה *Torah*. במשא ומתן *Be-masa u-matan*, when it comes to
business matters, לא הוו *lo havu*, no one honest person is left.
Okay. תנו רבנן *Tanu rabanan*. Now we get to an interesting story.
Maybe we only have five minutes but I think we'll get a
good way down here about teaching מעשה מרכבה Ma'aseh Merkavah. *Ma'aseh Merkava*.
Let's take a look. מעשה ברבן יוחנן בן זכאי שהיה רוכב על
החמור *Ma'aseh be-Rabban Yokhanan ben Zakai she-haya rokhev al ha-khamor*. Story of
רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai *Rabban Yokhanan ben Zakai*
who was on a donkey. והיה מהלך בדרך *Ve-haya mhalekh ba-derekh*. And
he was going on the way. ורבי אלעזר בן ערך מחמר אחריו
*Ve-Rabbi Elazar ben Arakh mkhamer akharav*. And רבי אלעזר בן ערך Rabbi
Elazar ben Arach *Rabbi Elazar ben Arakh*, who we know very little
of, was walking after him, after the donkey. אמר לו, Amar lo,
and he said to him, רבי, שנה לי sh'neili פרק אחד perek
echad במעשה מרכבה, b'Ma'aseh Merkavah, teach me something about the מעשה מרכבה.
Ma'aseh Merkavah Here we are, we're just walking on the way, we
have nothing to talk about, let's talk about מעשה
מרכבה. Ma'aseh Merkavah, אמר לו, amar lo, he said to him, לא
כך שניתי לכם, lo kach shaniti lachem, haven't I taught you, ולא
במרכבה ביחיד, v'lo b'merkava b'yachid, you can't teach מרכבה merkava even to
a single individual, אלא אם כן היה חכם מבין מדעתו, ela im
kein haya chacham meivin mida'ato, unless he can figure things out by
his own? So אמר לו, Amar lo, רבי, תרשיני לומר לפניך דבר
אחד שלמדתני, tarsheini lomar lefanecha davar echad shelimadtani, let me tell you
something that you taught us. Meaning, I'll show you what I was
able to figure out on my own, just in case you were
wondering, I am that person. So I'm going to tell you something
you taught me. Now again, it presumably means, you know, not that
I'm just going to tell you back something you taught me. You
didn't, you thought I wasn't picking up on what you were teaching,
I'm going to show you what I heard from what you were
teaching me.
אמר לו, Amar lo, אמור. Emor. He said, good, tell me. מיד
ירד רבן יוחנן בן זכאי מעל החמור, Miyad yarad Rabban Yochanan ben
Zakkai mei'al hachamor, so he got off the donkey, ונתעטף וישב על
האבן תחת הזית, v'nitatef v'yashav al ha'even tachat hazayit, and he sat
on a stone under an olive tree. You can imagine that every
section of this story is explained, you know, symbolically and metaphorically by
different people. אמר לו, so he said to him, רבי,
מפני מה ירדת מעל החמור? Rabbi, mipnei ma yaradta mei'al hachamor? Why'd
you get off the donkey? אמר, אפשר אתה דורש במעשה מרכבה ושכינה
עמנו ומלאכי השרת מלווין אותנו? efshar ata doreish b'ma'aseh merkava v'shchina imanu
u'malachei hashareit melavin otanu? Is it possible you'll be explicating מעשה מרכבה
Ma'aseh Merkavah, and the divine presence will be with us and the
heavenly angels will be accompanying us, ואני ארכב על החמור, v'ani erchav
al hachamor, and I should be on the donkey? I have to
do it for respect of the שכינה Shchina that is going to
be joining us. Again, so fascinating because רבי אלעזר בן ערך was
wise enough to understand what רבן יוחנן Rabban Yochanan was teaching, but
he didn't realize apparently the power of what was behind it. So
let's take a look. מיד פתח רבי אלעזר בן ערך במעשה מרכבה,
Miyad patach Rabbi Elazar ben Arach b'ma'aseh merkava, he began to expound
מעשה מרכבה, Ma'aseh Merkavah. ודרש, v'darash, and he explicated, וירדה אש מן
השמים, v'yarda eish min hashamayim, a fire came out of heaven, וסיבכה
את כל האילנות שבשדה, v'sibcha et kol ha'ilanot shebasadeh, and sort of
singed or surrounded all of the trees שבשדה, shebasadeh, פתחו כולם ואמרו
שירה, pitchu kulam v'amru shira, and they all opened up, all of
the trees presumably, and gave forth a song. ומה שירה אמרו, U'ma
shira amru, and what song did they say? הללו את ה' מן
הארץ תנינים וכל תהומות, Hallelu et Hashem min ha'aretz taninim v'chol tehomot,
עץ פרי וכל ארזים. eitz pri v'chol arazim. So all the trees
will praise God. הללויה. Halleluyah. נענה מלאך מן האש ואמר, Na'ana malach
min ha'eish v'amar, then the angel of the fire who was down,
who presumably had brought the fire, responded and said, הן הן מעשה
מרכבה. hein hein ma'aseh merkava. What you're telling, teaching, he's got it
exactly right, that is the doings of the divine chariot. So again,
notice by the way, right, the again, the relationship of earth and
heaven, the ability to access what's up in heaven. So before we
talked about praying and changing things in heaven, here you can bring
heaven down to earth. That's מעשה מרכבה, Ma'aseh Merkavah, to see the
vision and to bring heaven down to earth. הן הן מעשה מרכבה.
Hein hein ma'aseh merkava. עמד רבן יוחנן בן זכאי ונישקו על ראשו,
Amad Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai u'neshako al rosho, רבן יוחנן בן זכאי
got up and kissed him on his head, ואמר, v'amar, ברוך ה'
אלוהי ישראל, Baruch Hashem Elohei Yisrael, praise God, blessed is God, the
God of Israel, שנתן בן לאברהם אבינו, shenatan bein l'Avraham Avinu, he
gave such a son to Abraham our father, שיודע להבין ולחקור ולדרוש
במעשה מרכבה, sheyodeia l'havin u'lachkor v'lidrosh b'ma'aseh merkava, who knows how to
understand, maybe to understand
by understanding the
hints that I gave him, and to investigate and to expound in
the מעשה מרכבה. יש נאה דורש ואין נאה מקיים, Yeish na'eh doreish
v'ein na'eh mekayeim, there are those that expound beautifully and do not
fulfill beautifully, ויש נאה מקיים ואין נאה דורש, v'yeish na'eh mekayeim v'ein
na'eh doreish, fulfill but do not expound, אתה נאה דורש ונאה מקיים,
ata na'eh doreish v'na'eh mekayeim, you expound beautifully and fulfill. Now, of
course, the question is what fulfill is going on here. This is
a phrase used in another context which has to do with acting,
you know, in accordance with one's teaching. So the Bach switches the
gears and takes out the נאה מקיים na'eh mekayeim from this whole
thing. The Maharsha suggests it just means you expounded beautifully and it
actually corresponded to the truth, and that's the נאה מקיים. na'eh mekayeim.
אשריך אברהם אבינו, Ashrecha Avraham Avinu, praised are you Abraham our father,
שאלעזר בן ערך יצא מחלציך, she'Elazar ben Arach yatza mechalatzecha, that Elazar
ben Arach came out of your loins. Of course, why Abraham is
being brought into this context I don't know, what is the relationship
of Abraham? I mean, maybe he had that first direct communication with
God, but still, a little bit unclear what
the association is exactly with Abraham. What? ספר יצירה. Sefer Yetzirah. He
wrote the זהר. Zohar. He wrote the זהר? Zohar?
No, שמעון בר יוחאי,
Shimon bar Yochai, maybe he wrote the ספר יצירה. Sefer Yetzirah. Right.
Okay, is that what the footnote says? Alright. וכשנאמרו דברים לפני רבי
יהושע, U'keshenemru devarim lifnei Rabbi Yehoshua, now when this story was told
over to רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, היה הוא ורבי יוסי הכהן מהלכין
בדרך, haya hu v'Rabbi Yossi HaKohen mehalechin baderech, he and רבי יוסי
הכהן Rabbi Yossi HaKohen were going in the way, אמרו, they said,
oh well, they used an opportunity to talk about מעשה מרכבה, we'll
do the same. אף אני אדרוש במעשה מרכבה. Af ani edrosh b'ma'aseh
merkava. פתח רבי יהושע ודרש, Patach Rabbi Yehoshua v'darash, רבי יהושע Rabbi
Yehoshua opened up and expounded, ואותו היום תקופת תמוז היה, v'oto hayom
tkufat Tammuz haya, and it was a summer, middle of the summer,
ונתקשרו שמים בעבים, v'nitkashru shamayim be'avim, and the sky filled with clouds,
ונראה כמין קשת בענן, v'nira k'min keshet be'anan, and a rainbow appeared,
והיו מלאכי השרת מתקבצים ובאים לשמוע, v'hayu malachei hashareit mitkabtzim u'va'im lishmoa,
and the heavenly angels were coming to hear the shiur, כבני אדם
שמתקבצים ובאים לראות במזמוטי חתן וכלה, kivnei adam shemitkabtzim u'va'im lir'ot bemazmotei
chatan v'challa, like people who come to see like in the games
or in the rejoicing of a חתן וכלה, chatan v'challa, which is
interesting, why are the angels coming to hear? Don't they know better?
So, one hand they might be saying, like, really, like this amazing
statement like no, they could not understand better. what's happening up in
heaven and the angels. But it also seems to me that that's
why it gives the comparison of מזמוטי חתן וכלה, mazmutei chatan vechallah,
like you want to see people getting the pleasure and enjoyment of
it even if you're not necessarily being a part of that, even
if you're not necessarily learning something from that. One minute. הלך רבי
יוסי הכהן וסיפר דברים לפני רבי יוחנן
בן זכאי. Halach Rabbi Yosei HaKohen vesiper devarim lifnei Rabbi Yochanan ben
Zakkai. So Rabbi Yosei HaKohen, who was one of the pair, went
and told Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai about that amazing conversation that they
had with Rabbi Elazar ben Arach and Rabbi Yehoshua. ואמר אשריכם ואשרי
יולדתכם. Veamar ashreichem veashrei yoledetchem. So Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai, since he
gave this beautiful praise to Rabbi Elazar ben Arach, now he's going
to give a similar praise to Rabbi Yehoshua and Rabbi Yosei HaKohen.
Praise are you and praise are those that have given birth to
you. Not going all the way back to אברהם אבינו. Avraham Avinu.
אשרי עיני. Ashrei einai. Praise are my eyes שכך ראו shekach rau
that I have seen this. Meaning he saw the visions I saw
when I was doing it with Rabbi Elazar ben Arach and I've
seen that, you know, you also have been able to have these
types of experiences. ואף אני ואתם בחלומי, Veaf ani veatem bachalomi, and
even you and I in my dream, I saw מסובים. mesubim. I
saw we were reclining by הר סיני. Har Sinai. That's that image,
reclining? I mean, מסובים mesubim is something used when you eat. No,
there are the people that see God and ויחזו את האלהים ויאכלו
וישתו, vayichezu et HaElokim vayochlu vayishtu, and they ate and drank. So
maybe he's putting himself in that category of those that were at
הר סיני Har Sinai and had that vision of God and ate
and drank in God's presence. ונתנה עלינו בת קול מן השמים Venitna
aleinu bat kol min hashamayim and a heavenly voice came out from
heaven. עלו לכאן עלו לכאן. Alu lechan alu lechan. Come up here,
come up here. טרקלין, Traklin, right? Of course, as opposed to הר
סיני Har Sinai where it was where there was the boundaries
and people couldn't go
up. Here they're like on a higher level. They're being told to
come up, come up. טרקלין גדולים ומוצעות נאות מוצעות לכם. Traklin gedolim
umutzaot naot mutzaot lachem. Be, you know, big castles and beautiful cushions
are laid out for you. לכם אתם ותלמידיכם ותלמידי תלמידיכם. Lachem atem
vetalmideichem vetalmidei talmideichem. You and your students and your students' students. מזומנים
לכת שלישית. Mezumanin lechat shelishit. You are going to be in the
third group of people in the presence of God. So third, what
about first and second? Apparently that was like as high as they
could hope for. Okay, so we'll end here, we'll continue tomorrow. Just
want to say one thing about Rabbi Elazar ben Arach. We know
very little about Rabbi Elazar ben Arach except
the statement in פרקי אבות
Pirkei
Avot that says he
was like a מעין המתגבר. maayan hamitgaber. Okay, and that fits in
very perfectly with this that Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai thought you don't
know anything and he said no, you know what? I'm going to
here's what I have figured out from the little that you have
taught and that you have hinted to. So that's again the מעין
המתגבר maayan hamitgaber and he was then able to create, you know,
to even teach Rabbi Yochanan and create this enormous experience. Before we
adjourn today, we have a presentation of your birthday. מזל טוב Mazel
tov to our— Oh, thank you.
This
is
a wish and we have a contribution in your honor made to
the Institute of Rabbinic Discretion.
Oh, thank you so much, that's very kind.
Many returns from everybody in the— Oh,
thank you, thank you all very much.
It's very sweet, thank you. I thought that that's what the cake
was for, too. No, that's for something else. I made that. I
don't know, there's a whole big plate of cakes sitting there, I
don't know what that's
about. This is
for something last time
we— Oh, thank you very much, I really appreciate it.